Guide to the Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Post-1946 Printed Material, 1920-1987; Series VI; 5; (12 boxes)
  - Family and Friends
    - Lawrence, D.H. Mrs., 1950 Nov 1 (Box 24, Folder 408)
    - Lewis, Lloyd, 1949 Apr 22 (Box 24, Folder 409)
    - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1959-73, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 410)
    - LaMotte, Ellen, 1961 Mar 5 (Box 24, Folder 411)
    - Matisse, Henri, 1954-69 (Box 24, Folder 412-413)
    - MacPherson, Kenneth, 1971 Jun 18 (Box 24, Folder 414)
    - Metcalf, Addison, 1954-60 (Box 24, Folder 415)
    - Nadelman, Elie, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 416)
    - Nadelman, Elie Mrs., 1962 Mar 2 (Box 24, Folder 417)
    - Olivier, Fernande, 1955 Feb 5 (Box 24, Folder 418)
    - Picabia, Francis, 1953 Dec 11 (Box 24, Folder 419)
    - Picasso, Pablo, 1946-80 (Box 24, Folder 420)
    - Poe, Edgar Allen, 1963 Dec 1 (Box 24, Folder 421)
    - Rose, Sir Francis, 1949 Jul 4 (Box 24, Folder 422)
    - Sedgwick, Ellery, 1960 Apr 22 (Box 24, Folder 423)
    - Sitwell, Dame Edith, 1959 (Box 24, Folder 424)
    - Stein, Danny, 1962 Mar 21, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 425)
    - Stein, Fred, 1950 Apr (Box 24, Folder 426)
    - Stein, Leo, 1950 Jun 27 (Box 24, Folder 427)
    - Stettheimer, Florence, 1973 Feb 20 (Box 24, Folder 428)
    - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1946 Aug 18 (Box 24, Folder 429)
    - Strock, Hudson, 1976 Sep 23 (Box 24, Folder 430)
    - Thomson, Virgil, 1950-82, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 431-432)
    - Toklas, Alice B., 1954-73 (Box 24, Folder 433-434)
      See also: Oversize (for scrapbook of reviews), Box 40, folder 642
    - Ullman, Alice Woods, 1959 Jul 26 (Box 24, Folder 435)
    - Ullman, Eugene P., 1953 Apr 21
    - Van Doren, Mark, 1967 Dec 5 (Box 24, Folder 436)
    - Whitehead, Alfred North, 1947 Dec 31 (Box 24, Folder 437)
    - Whittemore, Thomas, 1950 Jun 9 (Box 24, Folder 438)
  - Works By and About Stein
    - Alphabets and Birthdays, 1957-58 (Box 25, Folder 439)
    - Anthologies, 1946-62 (Box 25, Folder 440)
    - Auction and Bookseller Catalogs, 1949-82 (Box 25, Folder 441)
    - The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas, 1955, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 442)
    - Aux Galeries Lafayette, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 442a)
      (facsimile of offprint of review of Rogue in The Sun, 1915 Mar 21)
    - Bee Time Vine, 1953 (Box 25, Folder 443)
    - Bilignin ceremony, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 444)
    - Bless You All, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 445)
      Programs and sheet music, signed by composers and others, of "A Rose is a Rose"
    - Blood on the Dining Room Floor, 1948-53, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 446)
    - Brewsie and Willie, 1947-78, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 447-449)
      Includes programs for stage adaptation by Ellen Violette and Lisbeth Blake (1952-56)
      See also: Oversize, Box 40, folder 643
    - Captain Walter Arnold, 1969 (Box 25, Folder 450)
    - A Circular Play, 1980 (Box 25, Folder 451)
    - Everybody's Autobiography, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 452)
    - Exercise d'analyse, 1984 (Box 25, Folder 453)
    - Exhibition--Art Gallery of Ontario, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 454)
    - Exhibition--Bancroft Library, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 455)
    - Exhibition--Le Centre Culturel Americain, Paris, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 456)
    - Exhibition--Four Americans in Paris, 1970-71, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 457-458)
    - Exhibition--Millersville State College, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 459)
    - Exhibition--Francis Rose, 1949-80 (Box 26, Folder 460)
    - Exhibitions--miscellaneous, 1949-87, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 461)
    - Faust, 1951-83, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 462-464)
    - Fernhurst, Q.E.D., 1973 (Box 26, Folder 465)
    - The First Reader, 1946-79, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 466-467)
    - The Flowers of Friendship, 1953, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 468)
    - Four in America, 1947, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 469)
    - Four Saints in Three Acts, 1941-1986, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 470-473)
    - Four Saints in Three Acts, 1941-1986, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 474-477)
      Includes Italian translation of libretto
    - Gertrude Stein...and a Companion, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 478)
    - Gertrude Stein's America, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 478a)
    - Gertrude Stein's Gertrude Stein, 1965-73 (Box 27, Folder 479)
    - Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein, Gertrude Stein, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 480)
    - "Gertrude Stein--Her Words and Her Ideas," lectures by Julian Sawyer, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 481)
    - Gertrude Stein on Picasso, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 482)
    - "Gertrude Stein on Records", ca. 1952 (Box 27, Folder 482a)
      (promotional sheet featuring reviews of Stein recordings issued by Dorian Records)
    - How Writing is Written, 1974 (Box 27, Folder 483)
    - I Like it to Be a Play, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 484)
    - Ida, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 485)
    - In a Garden, 1949-65, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 486)
    - In Circles, 1967-83 (Box 27, Folder 487)
    - Ladies' Voices, 1952-58 (Box 27, Folder 488)
    - Last Operas and Plays, 1949, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 489-491)
      posthumous reviews, clippings
    - Lectures in America, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 492)
    - Letter to Freddy, 1948 (Box 27, Folder 493)
    - Listen to Me, 1974-80 (Box 27, Folder 494)
    - Long Island University, C.W. Post Center--American Theatre Festival, 1975 (Box 27, Folder 495)
    - Made by Two, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 496)
      See also: Oversize, folder 644
    - The Making of Americans, 1972-83, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 497-498)
    - A Manoir, 1977, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 499)
    - Many Many Women, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 500)
    - Messages. A Play., 1976 (Box 28, Folder 501)
    - Mrs. Reynolds, 1952-53, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 502)
    - The Mother of Us All, 1942-87, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 503-509)
    - The Mother of Us All, course at University of California, Berkley, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 510)
    - A Novel of Thank-You, 1958-59 (Box 28, Folder 511)
    - Painted Lace, 1955 (Box 28, Folder 512)
    - A Patriotic Leading, 1953 (Box 28, Folder 513)
    - Photograph, 1977 (Box 28, Folder 514)
    - Pink Melon Joy - Gertrude Stein Out Loud, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 515)
    - Quod Erat Demonstrandum, 1950-51 (Box 29, Folder 516)
    - Say it with Flowers, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 517)
    - Selected Writings, 1946-47, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 518)
    - "Simply Stein", n.d. (Box 29, Folder 519)
    - Stanzas in Meditation, 1956-57, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 520)
    - "Sydney Omarr's Almanac", 1956 (Box 29, Folder 521)
      Transcript of radio show of Gertrude Stein
    - Tender Buttons, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 522)
    - Three Lives, 1951 (Box 29, Folder 523)
    - Three Sisters Who Are Not Sisters, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 524)
    - Two, 1951-54, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 525)
    - Two (hitherto unpublished) Poems, 1948 Mar (Box 29, Folder 525a)
    - UCLA Collection, 1974-75 (Box 29, Folder 526)
    - UCLA 100th Birthday Celebration for Gertrude Stein, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 527)
    - UCLA Symposium: "Concerning Gertrude Stein", 1984 (Box 29, Folder 528)
    - Wars I Have Seen, 1946-48 (Box 29, Folder 529)
    - Washington University Celebration: "Happy Birthday Gertrude Stein!", 1975 (Box 29, Folder 530)
    - A Wedding Bouquet, 1949-83, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 531)
    - What Happened, 1947-64, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 532)
    - When This You See Remember Me [book by W. G. Rogers], n.d. (Box 29, Folder 533)
    - "When This You See Remember Me" [film by Perry Miller Adato], 1970-80 (Box 29, Folder 534)
    - When This You See Remember Me [play], 1959, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 535)
    - The Women in the Garden, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 536)
    - The World is Round [dance opera], 1952-66, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 537-538)
    - Yes is for a Very Young Man, 1945-84, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 539-552)
      Includes: letter to Carl Van Vechten from 48 Theater, and sheet of background music.
      See also: Oversize, Box 40, folder 645
    - Mixed programs featuring Stein writings, 1954-83, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 553)
    - Miscellaneous mentions of Gertrude Stein, 1946-57, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 554)
  - Issues of magazines and printed items with mentions of Gertrude Stein, ca. 1946-83 (Box 31, Folder -)
  - Issues of magazines and printed items with mentions of Gertrude Stein, ca. 1946-83 (Box 32, Folder -)
  - Issues of magazines and printed items with mentions of Gertrude Stein, ca. 1946-83 (Box 33, Folder -)
- Artworks, 1914-1939; Series VII; 2; (1 box) + separate items
  Series VII, Artworks, is arranged alphabetically by name of artist. Reference prints for items in this series are found following Series IX.
  - BERMAN, EUGENE
    - Trees at Bilignin, 1929 (Box 34, Folder 555)
      ink on paper
  - GROSSER, MAURICE
    - Virgil Thomson, n.d. (Box art, Folder 556)
      oil on canvas, framed
  - HURD, CLEMENT
    - [wallpaper from his illustrations from Gertrude Stein's The World is Round], ca. 1939 (Box bsd, folder 557)
      printed paper
  - LANE, CAMILLE
    - Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas (Box art, Folder 558)
      oil on canvas, framed, signed
  - MARCOUSSIS, ANDRE
    - [portrait of Gertrude Stein], 1934 (Box art, Folder 558a)
      engraving on paper, framed, signed
  - MILLER, LEON GORDON
    - Gertrude Stein and Basket, ca. 1949 (Box 34, Folder 559)
      woodcut on paper - two impressions with presentation letters to Carl Van Vechten and Thornton Wilder
  - PICASSO, PABLO RUIZ
    - Still Life with Calling Card, 1914 (Box art, Folder 560)
      mixed media on paper, signed on back
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted. Artwork is on permanent loan to the Yale University Art Gallery. For more information please consult the appropriate curator.
  - ROSE, SIR FRANCIS CYRIL
    - Death, or Le nouveau né, 1934 Sep 18 (Box 34, Folder 561)
      ink, watercolor, and casein on paper, signed and dated
    - [Head of a woman], 1933 (Box 34, Folder 562)
      watercolor on paper, signed and dated
    - [Mougins], 1933 (Box 34, Folder 563)
      ink and watercolor on paper, signed and dated
    - [Spanish woman with still life], 1934 (Box 34, Folder 564)
    - [Still life], 1933 (Box 34, Folder 565)
      graphite on paper, signed and dated
    - [Studies for Homage to Gertrude Stein], 1947-48 (Box 34, Folder 566-566c)
      watercolor on paper
    - [Studies for Homage to Gertrude Stein], 1947-48 (Box bsd, folder 566)
    - [Studies for Homage to Gertrude Stein], 1947-48 (Box bsd, folder 566e)
    - [Two heads], 1934 (Box 34, Folder 567)
    - [Woman in black], 1934 (Box 34, Folder 568)
- Objects, 1949, n.d.; Series VIII; 1; (1 box)
  Series VIII, Objects, is listed by according to physical arrangement. Reference prints for items in this series are found following Series IX.
  - The Gertrude Stein mug, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 569)
    Ceramic, manufactured by Fitz & Floyd
  - Scarf, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 570)
    Silk fabric with "A rose is a rose is a rose" and other Stein symbols and facsimiles of Stein handwriting designed by Francis Rose and manufactured by Aschen.
  - Plant greens (dried) from Gertrude Stein's garden, 1949 (Box 35, Folder 571)
  - Lapel button: "Gertrude Stein Lives 1874-1974", n.d. (Box 35, Folder 572)
  - Buttons and beads (Box 41)
    "Gertrude Stein buttons--beads given to Isabel Wilder by Alice B. Toklas and given by Miss Wilder for YCAL." Includes a variety of buttons, a clasp, an amber pendant, and a string of blue and white beads.
- Film & Sound Recordings, ca. 1927-1964; Series IX; (8 items)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Home movie (16mm film) taken by Julian Stein of: Michael Stein's home, designed by Le Corbusier, in Garches, France; and Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas at the Hotel Pernollet in Belley, France, ca. 1927 (Box film, Folder 573-577)
    Original film and duplicate of film.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Reference copies available.
  - Columbia University Press Contemporary Poets Series. Gertrude Stein reading: Matisse, If I Told Him, The Making of Americans, A Valentine for Sherwood Anderson, AND Selections from Madame Recamier. Three double-sided 12" 78 RPM records, credited to ERPI Picture Consultants. Recorded at Columbia University during the American tour, 1934-35 (Box HSR)
    Reference copy available at the Historical Sound Recordings department of Sterling Library
  - "Gertrude Stein read by Gertrude Stein" The Making of Americans, A Valentine to Sherwood Anderson, If I told him, Matisse, and Selections from Madame Recamier. (reissue of ERPI recording, above). One double-sided 12" 33 RPM disc, credited to Harcourt, Brace and Company., 1951 (Box HSR)
  - Wars I Have Seen, read by Norma Chambers. An Isabelle Archer Dyer memorial talking book solely for the use of the blind. Recorded by the American foundation for the blind. One double- sided 78 RPM disc. Pressed by RCA Victor. (Pages 1 and 2 of "20 records" only), 1946 (Box HSR)
  - Alice Toklas reading from The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas and The Alice B. Toklas Cookbook. Contents include: The Garden at Bilignin, Haschich Fudge, Before I came to Paris, AND On first meeting with Gertrude Stein. Recording made April 29, 1960. One double-sided 12" 33-1/3 RPM disc. Pressed by Verve. (Box HSR)
  - Gertrude Stein Interviewed by William Lundell. Recorded October 12, 1934 on NBC. (Original copy of tape in storage, Two use copies available on reel-to-reel tape: One includes Gertrude Stein reading from her works - three items from the ERPI disc: Matisse, If I told him, AND A Valentine to Sherwood Anderson AND four items from a Spoken Arts recording: She bowed to her brother, Georges Hugnet, Fifteenth of November, AND Portrait of Christian Bérard. One includes a recording given by Sam Steward of Alice B. Toklas interviewed on a German television program. (Box HSR)
  - Interview with Paul Padgette concerning exhibition of Stein material in San Francisco, 1964 Jun 17 (Box HSR)
- Reference Prints for Artworks and Objects, 0.5; (1 box)
  - Photographic prints (Box 36, Folder 578)
- Oversize, 1946-1980; 7.5; (4 boxes)
  Oversize, contains material from Series I, III, IV, and VI, arranged in series order.
  - WRITINGS - GERTRUDE STEIN BIBLIOGRAPHY
    - Letter to Rousseau Voorhies
      - Printed version, Chicago Sunday Magazine of Books [with letter from Norman Holmes Pearson to "Gilbert"], 1946 Sep 8 (Box 37, Folder 579)
    - The World is Round
      - Young Scott Books edition, 1966, illustrated by Clement Hurd
        - Rough pencil sketches for illustrations, [ca. 1964] (Box 37, Folder 580-582)
        - Linoleum print drafts of illustrations, [ca. 1964] (Box 37, Folder 583-609)
        - Final linoleum color studies and separations, [ca. 1964] (Box 38, Folder 610-633)
  - WRITINGS - WRITINGS OF ALICE B. TOKLAS
    - What is Remembered
      - Printed excerpt entitled "Brilliant Wonderland of Alice B. Toklas," Life International, 1963 Mar 25 (Box 38, Folder 634)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Byrnside, Ronald
      - "The Garden," [cantata score], photocopy, corrected, 1959 (Box 39, Folder 635)
    - Harrison, Gilbert A.
      - 90th birthday book of Alice B. Toklas, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 636)
    - Martin, Vernon
      - "Ladies' Voices, a dramatic opera," [score], photocopy, corrected, 1955 (Box 39, Folder 637)
    - Rorem, Ned
      - Broadside - facsimile of holograph page of "I am Rose", 1955 Sep 29 (Box 39, Folder 638)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - People and Places, undated (Box 39, Folder 638a)
    - Exhibits, 1947 Jul 18 (Box 39, Folder 639)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL POST-1946
    - Clippings, General - about Gertrude Stein - Stein and Art, 1946-66 (Box 39, Folder 640)
    - Clippings - Critical and Biographical, 1947, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 641)
    - Clippings - Toklas, Alice B. - Scrapbook of reviews of books by ABT, compiled by Ray Lewis White, 1954-63 (Box 40, Folder 642)
    - Brewsie and Willie, 1952 May 5 (Box 40, Folder 643)
    - Made By Two [theater poster], 1980 Mar (Box bsd, folder 644)
    - Yes is for a Very Young Man, 1952 (Box 40, Folder 645)